Garrison Family Papers, 1694-2005 (bulk 1830-1950)
Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College
- SERIES IV. WRITINGS AND SPEECHES 1829-1999, 7.75 linear ft.
  For WLG (1874) there are school essays, and speeches and writings by topic (abolition, peace, race issues, taxation, suffrage etc.) Within this alphabetical list is a group of speeches entitled Technology Talks (1924 and 1933) and talks to the Tuesday Club (1931-40). There are two folders of miscellaneous speeches and writings which concern other topics, including introductory remarks for Booker T. Washington and Charles Eastman. Within this alphabetical list is poetry which includes complete texts and notes and some background material he used to compose the verse. When possible the poetry is arranged by subject (i.e. Anniversary, birthday and commemorative verse, Cape Cod, Coffin and Burr, Harvard (class reunions and other activities), poetry written anonymously under the initials GLW). Otherwise the poems are organized by date; those with no dates are alphabetical by title. The largest group of poems are the commemorative poems written in memoriam and in celebration of others. These include family members, especially the Villards, his wife and children, as well as friends and neighbors. These are arranged in a separate alphabetical section by person, with two folders of poems for miscellaneous people. The final group of poetry includes unidentified, undated and incomplete items.
  David Lloyd Garrison's autobiographical work Early and Late (1994), Lucy McKim Garrison's transcriptions original slave songs (which are located in the Flat File), and a compilation of Garrison family writings, Garrisoniana (1869-1902) are also noteworthy.
- SERIES V. FINANCIAL MATERIALS (1812-1993), 4.75 linear ft.
  This series contains financial material related to twelve members of the Garrison Family. It is arranged alphabetically by person and contains tax information, probate and estate records, inventories, items related to real estate, ledgers, business diaries, expense logs and related correspondence. Financial/business correspondence related to property owned at Cape Cod is located in SERIES VI. SUBJECT FILES - Wianno. The largest amounts of material relate to both the WLG (1838)'s and WLG (1874)'s business and personal affairs.
  WLG (1838)'s business material includes brokerage (1873) and mortgage (1889-1901) books and an investment ledger (1889-92), as well as a sales journal (1877-78). There is material related to trust accounts he handled for Mary E. Robinson, Theodore Dwight Weld, Eliza Church, and Theodore Grinké Weld (1875-1903). The personal material includes correspondence (1903-10), estate matters (1892-1936), real estate (1903-10), personal securities (1903), expenses (1890-1904), and ledgers (1872-1900).
  WLG (1874)'s business material consists of diaries (1898-1904), Perry Coffin & Burr material, including correspondence (1900-57), trust accounts for Mary Randall (1902-07) and Theodore Grimké Weld (1905-23), and correspondence and legal papers for his partnership. There is considerable overlap with SERIES III. CORRESPONDENCE because WLG (1874) handled business affairs for family members and friends. His personal material includes estate items (1928), house construction and repair correspondence (1901-17), and personal ledgers (1907-38).
- SERIES VI. SUBJECT FILES 1810-1966, 9.75 linear ft.
  This series, arranged alphabetically, contains printed material, memorabilia, and related correspondence on forty-one subjects which were of interest to the Garrisons, or about organizations in which they were involved. These topics range far and wide: reform movements (free trade, single tax, suffrage), minor controversies (the dangers of football and the reform of hockey rules), health issues (anti-vaccination, osteopathy, homeopathy), schools and camps (Auburn Female Seminary, Eagleswood School, Country Day School for Boys, Roxbury Latin School, Harvard University, Sidney Lanier Camp), and Garrison homes and retreats (Wianno). Some of the subjects relate to only one Garrison, others relate to several and span the generations. The largest and/or richest subjects are abolition (1833-1962), anti-vaccination (1895-1938), free trade and tariff reform (1887-1959), Harvard University (1891-1967), immigration (1871-1924), pacifism (1839-1940), race (1888-1936), single tax (1877-1947), suffrage (1856-1952), temperance (1828-1908), and Wianno (1905-1966). Anti-imperialism, free trade, single tax, and pacifism contain interrelated material. Many of these subjects are included in the WLG (1838) scrapbooks in SERIES IX. SERIES I. BIOGRAPHICAL MATERIAL, SERIES IV. SPEECHES AND WRITING and within the correspondence in SERIES III. Some of the subjects include periodicals and organizations which are listed separately. In addition there are general periodicals and organizations unrelated to any specific subject.
  The abolition files are particularly significant. These include published material on the American (1833-84) and Massachusetts (1837-41) Anti-Slavery Societies; "Anti-Slavery Reminiscences" by Elizabeth Buffum Chase; correspondence of Maria Weston Chapman, (1835, 1837), James Miller McKim (1849, 1866) and George Thompson (1835); material related to The Liberator including a subscription letter (1839); memorabilia (1858-61); printed material, including Anti-Slavery Tracts (1860, n.d.); general articles and clippings (1854-1948) and; pamphlets (1850-85) and specific printed material on the Fugitive Slave Law (1851-80) and the Kansas/Nebraska Act (1854-60). A run of The Liberator is located in the SSC Periodicals collection. British abolitionist George Thompson came to the United States with a stipend from the Anti-Slavery Women of Glasgow and Edinburgh in 1834. His letters (Feb-Apr 1835) are reports of this trip written to Miss Smeal and the Committee of the Glasgow Ladies. Correspondence of Maria Weston Chapman which includes a "Report to the Ladies of Scotland" (1835) is related to the Thompson letters. There is also a record of departed abolitionists (circa 1880) and material related to abolition reunions and anniversaries, (1886-89, n.d.). Items related to the American Freedman's Union Commission (1869, n.d.) are included in this file.
  There is documentation of an interesting incident involving the propriety of female store clerks. In 1849, women's rights reformers Elizabeth McClintock and Anna Southwick applied for a position in the Philadelphia wholesale business of Edward M. Davis (Lucretia Mott's son-in-law). Elizabeth Cady Stanton wrote a letter in support of the women's application. Davis brought the matter before his male clerks and in the end the application was refused. Some of the employees drew caricatures of female clerks. Lucretia Mott sent the drawings to McClintock who responded in kind, enclosing drawings and a "drama." Most of the drawings are unsigned, but it is presumed that those which portray women clerks in a more positive light were drawn by McClintock or Maria Mott Davis. In addition to the drawing and skit, this file contains correspondence and items from E.M Davis Co.
  Free trade and tariff reform is documented by several free trade organizations: American Free Trade League (1889-1917), Free Trade League (1919-21), International Free Trade League (1918-26), and New England Free Trade League (1896-98). WLG (1838) was secretary of the American Free Trade League and edited the Free Trade Broadside of which there are copies from 1905 to 1916. Frank Wright Garrison was on the Executive Committee for the International Free Trade League and WLG (1874) was a member. In addition to executive committee minutes and printed material, there is a long sequence of related correspondence (1917-59) as well as clippings, pamphlets, and flyers.
  The Harvard University material relates primarily to WLG (1874), class of 1897, with a small amount of material related to David Lloyd Garrison, class of 1928. It contains class reunion material, correspondence and printed items on eight Harvard related organizations including D.K.E. (1891-92), the Harvard Club of Boston (1912-41), the Harvard Liberal Club of Boston (1918-21) and Harvard Total Abstinence League (1912, n.d.). There is also some miscellaneous correspondence (1895-1960).
  The immigration file relates primarily to Chinese immigration and includes material on the Chinese Defense Fund (1903-04), Chinese Equal Rights League (1892), and National Liberal Immigration League (1907-08). There are quite a few printed items (1885-1924) including pamphlets, articles, clippings, and related correspondence (1871-1908).
  There are thirty-one separately filed organizations plus ten folders of small amounts of organizational material. These organizations with items dating from 1897 to 1964 represent the wide range of interests and reform movements in which the Garrisons were involved. These range from liberal causes (American Civil Liberties Union, American Friends Service Committee, Free Religious Association of America, and League for Democratic Control) to conservation and birding organizations (Massachusetts Audubon Society, Nature Conservancy, and Nuttall Ornithological Club) and genealogical societies (Massachusetts Society of Colonial Dames and New England Historic Genealogical Society).
  The Garrison summer retreat was located on Cape Cod, at Wianno in Osterville, Massachusetts. Osterville material consists of reports, correspondence, clippings, and printed material on the Osterville Free Public Library. (WLG (1874) was on its board of trustees for many years.) There are also items related to reunions of residents of Osterville (1905-07) plus miscellaneous historical items (1877-1969). Wianno documents include blueprints (1912-27); maintenance, insurance, real estate and miscellaneous correspondence (1905-50); deeds, titles and inventories (1920-43); and correspondence, organizational documents and printed material on the on the Wianno Club (1904-33).
  The pacifism file contains correspondence and printed material (1907-25); a file on military training (1904-26); and correspondence and printed material on peace organizations including American Union Against Militarism, the Women's Peace Party (1915-17), and the Women's Peace Society (1920-25).
  There are twelve periodical titles, including an issue of the Boston Patriot (1810), The Diamond (1851-52) edited by George Garrison while a student at the Hopedale Home School, and The Liberator edited by Max Eastman (1917-18).
  There is an extensive and rich file of race related to racial discrimination. Subjects include anti-lynching (1888-1904), education (1894-1930), Negro troops (1898-1906), suffrage (1898-1906), and miscellaneous printed material (1895-1914). The education file contains correspondence and printed material on Berea College (1894-09), Calhoun Colored School (1909-26), Forsythe Normal and Industrial School (1902-18), Hampton Normal and Agriculture Institute (1919-21), and Tuskegee Institute (1985-1930).
  The largest file in this series is on the single tax. There is extensive correspondence especially with political reformer and single taxer Daniel Kiefer, writings of Henry George, and records of fifteen separate single tax organizations including various state single tax leagues, the Single Tax Party, and the United Committee for the Taxation of land Values. There are runs of eleven single tax periodicals. Printed material includes articles and pamphlets (1887-1935), clippings (1888-1928), "quotable authorities" collected by WLG (1838) (1887-1905), and miscellaneous material (1887-1932).
  WLG (1838), Ellen Wright Garrison, Eleanor Garrison, Agnes Garrison, WLG (1874), and Edith Stephenson Garrison were all suffragists. There is a particularly rich collection of suffrage items related to their activities. There is also suffrage material elsewhere, especially in SERIES III. CORRESPONDENCE, SERIES IV. WRITINGS AND SPEECHES, and in SERIES IX. WRIGHT FAMILY. The file contains correspondence (1898-1952); printed material and clippings, (1867-916) from both the British and American suffrage movement; memorabilia (1900-50); records of nine suffrage organizations; and documents related to three suffrage/woman's right conventions (1856, 1870, 1872).
  The temperance file is related to both alcohol and tobacco. It contains articles, clippings, pamphlets, and miscellaneous printed material (1879-1908), information on the Massachusetts Total Abstinence Society (n.d.), and the Women's Christian Temperance Union (1919). Of particular interest is an issue of the National Philanthropist (1828) edited by WLG (1805).
- SERIES VII. PHOTOGRAPHS 1839-1998, 12.75 linear ft.
  This series is divided into six subseries: Family, Friends and associates, Subjects, Albums, Cased images, and Oversize material.
  The first subseries includes photographs of the following family groups: Bliss, Chubb, Emerson, Garrison, Harwood, Norton, Phoutrides, Stephenson, Villard, and Wright. Women are filed under their married names except for those of Ellen Wright Garrison with her siblings which are located with the Wright Family. They are arranged alphabetically; photographs with multiple family members located under the name of the father. Additional photographs of individuals can be found in family groups, Albums, Cased images and Oversize material, and in the Sophia Smith Collection Flat File.
  The Friends and associates subseries includes photographs of individuals the Garrisons knew personally as well as photographs collected by the Garrisons. They are arranged alphabetically and include photographs of such notables as Lydia Maria Child, Frederick Douglass, George Eliot, Sara Jane Lippincott, Harriet Tubman, Isabella Beecher Hooker, Lucretia Coffin Mott, Emmeline Pankhurst, Theodore Parker, Hattie and Robert Purvis, Caroline Severance, Lucy Stone, and Wendell Phillips. There are additional photographs of famous friends contained in two albums located in the fourth subseries in box 215.
  The Subjects subseries includes photographs arranged by topic. These include abolition, suffrage, and houses and vacation places. There are photographs of abolitionist groups at Ambleside and Lucy Stone's House as well as the Executive Committee of the Pennsylvania Anti Slavery Society. The suffrage photographs include two groups: one of which includes Susan B. Anthony, Rebecca Spring, Charlotte Wills, and Caroline Wills, and another of Anthony, Carrie Chapman Catt, Lila Sweet Martin, Anna Howard Shaw, Harriet May Mills, and Lucy Anthony. There is also a photograph of New York suffragists in "farmerette" costumes and suffrage parades. The Houses and Vacation places are arranged alphabetically; the family homes by family (Benson, Coffin-Mott, Garrison) and then by location. The largest group of photographs is of Wianno, the Garrisons summer "colony" on Cape Cod and it includes the various cottages as well as land and seascapes.
  The next three subseries are arranged randomly according to size The Albums contain both family and non-family photographs, some of which may be duplicated elsewhere in the series. There are two albums of negatives. Some of the photographs have either been removed from their albums, or the pages removed from their bindings for preservation reasons.
  The Cased images (arranged by large, medium and small) include tintypes, daguerreotypes, and ambrotypes. Those of the Wright family are particularly fine. The Oversize material contains photographs of family including family groups, for example Thanksgiving 1886, Frank Wright and Mildred Yarnall Garrison's wedding photograph, and school athletic team and class photographs of various Garrisons, especially WLG (1874). Photographs located in the Flat File are listed at the end of the box list with the rest of the Flat File items.
- SERIES VIII. MEMORABILIA 1694-1984, 6.25 linear ft.
  This series is arranged in two subseries. The first, Family, contains Garrison family memorabilia which encompasses either more than one Garrison or is unidentified. This subseries contains family games (n.d.), valentines and greeting card (n.d.), material on character analysis (1913-50), numerology and metaphysics (1922-26), and a box of medals and ribbons (1895-1914). Of particular interest are a series of cookbooks, household lists, accounts, recipes, and an arithmetic primer. Although many have names attached to them, their origin is unclear. It is assumed that the cookbooks were passed down through generations because the handwriting varies throughout. The earliest is dated 1694 and the latest 1834, although many are undated.
  Subseries two, Garrison Family contains memorabilia for twenty-eight individual Garrisons, arranged alphabetically. The largest group of material belongs to David Lloyd Garrison. Included are his art work (1918-87) (painting, drawing and art notes); birding material (1936-84) (notebooks of birds, bird records); military papers (1941-47); and travel notebooks (1947-85). Ellen Wright Garrison's material includes her hair collection and paper dolls. Items of WLG (1805) include an address book listing donations to fugitive slaves, and autopsy report (1869), and documents related to the purchase of the family home at Rockledge (1853-64). Memorabilia of WLG (1838) and WLG (1874) contains significant amounts of collected material (verse, jokes, quotes). There is a handwriting analysis for WLG (1838) and a notebook of writings from an Osterville tea (1877). There is Harvard memorabilia (1892-1931), juvenilia (1883), travel notes (1897, 1926) and a wedding guest list (1901) belonging to WLG (1874).
- SERIES IX. WRIGHT FAMILY 1806-1970, 8.5 linear ft.
  Ellen Wright married WLG (1838) in 1864. This series contains genealogical and biographical materials, correspondence, writings, and memorabilia, related to five generations of her family. "Wright family" is used loosely to include the Coffins and the Motts and their ancestors and descendants. Photographs of the Wright family are located in SERIES VII. PHOTOGRAPHS. This series is divided into three subseries: Biographical materials and memorabilia, Correspondence, and Writings.
  Biographical materials contains genealogical notes, correspondence and charts, anecdotes, poems and miscellaneous memorabilia. In Their Several Generations by Amice Mac Donnell Lee relates to the Yarnall family. Following this general material are biographical materials and memorabilia related to twenty-three family members. Of particular interest is the material related to Lucretia Mott, Peter Pelham, and the Wrights.
  Lucretia Coffin Mott's file contains clippings and printed material (1873-1930), and memorabilia which includes items related to the Motts' 50th wedding anniversary (1861). Items related to Peter Pelham include a notice of his death, accounts of a shipment of the Pelham's belongings to Florida (1824), and the settling of his estate (1827). Included in this subseries is a "Sketch of the life and character of David Wright" by Theodore M. Pomeroy (1898) and personal reminiscences of his life which he wrote in 1886. Martha Coffin Wright's biographical file includes a sketch written by Eliza Wright Osborne in the 1890s. In this sketch Osborne mentions a will written by Martha when she was a 15 years old. In 2001 her great-great grandson, James D. Livingston provided a copy, which is now included with the sketch. There are also certificates, obituaries, condolence letters, her final will (1864), and a document of disassociation from the Society of Friends (1825). In addition there are her account books (1829-52), drawings, collected verse and a small notebook entitled "Excerpts from the Portfolio of Josiah Landon, 1810" written in her hand.
  The second subseries, Correspondence, is divided into two sections; Letters from the Wrights and Letters to the Wrights. It includes family letters between spouses, siblings, cousins, friends, parents and children. They not only provide a view of nineteenth century social history and family life, but also give valuable insights into abolition, suffrage, women's rights and the people involved in those movements. The letters are interspersed with drawings and full of wit and humor. It should be noted that although they are arranged alphabetically by author, many were evidently handed around before being sent and are authored by two or more people, and many of these letters are round robin and were written to a number of different people. Also, in order to save paper, some letters were written in the blank spaces of other letters and some are written with the script going in two or three directions. Many of these letters have been photocopied for preservation purposes, some have been transcribed and typed copies have been included with the handwritten counterparts. There are also hand written copies made by Martha Coffin Wright for some of the letters.
  Of special note are letters written from Eagleswood School by Anna Coffin Temple Brown to Lucretia Coffin Mott and from Anna Davis Hallowell to Ellen Wright Garrison; Civil War letters from William Pelham Wright (1861-63), from his friend Andrew Cowan to William and David Wright (1862-63), and from Marianna Pelham Mott while she was at Gettysburg caring for her injured brother William (1863); and European travel letters from Marianna Pelham Mott (1855-69), Thomas Mott (1855-56), and Eliza Wright Osborne (1889, 1903). The letters among Lucretia Coffin Mott, Martha Coffin Wright, Susan B. Anthony, Elizabeth Cady Stanton, Ellen Wright Garrison, Ida Husted Harper, and Victoria Claflin Woodhull provide a particularly detailed description of the seeds of the American women's movement, and the planning of the early women's right conventions, especially the first in 1848 and the third in 1856.
  Of further interest are early Pelham family letters to Martha Coffin Wright (1824-65); letters from Putnam Catlin, father of artists Julius and George Catlin, to Martha Coffin Wright (1828-39); and letters from Henry Blackwell (1869), Matilda Joslyn Gage (1870-72), Lucretia and Martha's cousins Mary Hussey Earle (1842-75) and Phebe Hussey Gardner (1843), Sara Jane Lippincott (Grace Greenwood) (1860-65), Wendell Phillips (1860), Parker Pillsbury (1869-73), Theodore Dwight Weld and Angelina Grimké Weld (1854-62), and a fugitive slave, L. M. Worden (1845-70).
  Writings, the third subseries, includes Hints to Young People On The Duties of Civil Life (1826) by James Mott, and miscellaneous writings of Lucretia Coffin Mott (1828-69) including her Discourse on Women (1850, 1869), a discourse at a Friends Meeting in New York (1866), and a statement to the Equal Rights Convention at Albany (1866). Some of these writings are copies of originals located at the Huntington Library, Swarthmore Peace Collection, and the Historical Society of Pennsylvania. There are also original and typed copies of Martha Coffin Wright's diaries (1854-74) and her poetry (1844-64). Although the diaries are short entry, they contain references to such notables as Harriet Tubman, Elizabeth Cady Stanton, Susan B. Anthony, and Lucy Stone. Her miscellaneous writings include a draft of "Hints for Wives" which was read by Lucretia Coffin Mott at the Seneca Falls convention (1848). In addition, there are the Civil War writings of William Pelham Wright about the First New York Battery and a diary (1862). The former includes a list of officers, causalities and battles in which the Battery was engaged.
- SERIES X. STEPHENSON FAMILY (1818-1973), 1.75 linear ft.